Hey guys, Shan this side. Welcome back
to the channel and till now in the fall
tolerant microservices we have seen rate
limiter bulkhead retry and today we will
see a circuit breaker. So let's start
without wasting any time.
What does circuit breaker says?
This pattern prevents an application to
make repeated calls to downstream
service that is likely to fail. Okay. So
we'll come to this line again but see
this diagram. So let's say our
application is order service right and
we and this product is a downstream. So
order is invoking product for now assume
that this product service is
unavailable. So no matter how many times
you call this call will fail. Right? So
product service is down. No matter how
many times whether you are doing a retry
of the same call or whether you are
making a totally different call it will
fail. So there is some disadvantages for
it. The first disadvantage is we put
unnecessarily
add load to the product service and
because of that product service might
take longer time to recover. So see
product service is already unavailable
right it is facing some issue and we are
adding more load to it. So there is a
chance that product service might take
little longer time to
uh come up in the healthy state.
The second is order service is
unnecessarily wasting it resources both
latency and the thread blocking. So just
see that if let's say there are
thousands and thousands of calls and
product service is unavailable they all
will fail. So order service is
unnecessarily wasting its resource
because there is a latency involved. It
calls it it wait for the product service
to response till time out and then only
it will send to the client that hey it's
a fail some 5xx error something okay so
there is definitely increase in the
latency and you are unnecessarily
blocking your thread on this call okay
so there is no need because even if you
wait it the call is likely going to fail
because the product service is
unavailable
But now
what's the solution? How does order
service know
when to stop the downstream call? like
we are saying that hey order don't make
unnecessarily call to product because it
is unavailable
right but how order knows that when it
is unavailable when it is up and when I
have okay if it is unavailable when
again I have to restart so something has
to instruct this
uh you can say that knowledge somebody
has to put this knowledge to order right
then only order would be able to stop or
restart the call.
So who add that knowledge that is
circuit breaker.
Okay. So again revisiting the line which
we went ahead in the first place it
prevents an application to make repeated
calls to downstream service that is
likely to fail. So see this diagram now.
So now order service let's say make
initial calls and both got failed. So
now we will put some threshold value
that hey if this many calls get failed
means there is some issue with the
product. So don't make any further calls
to it. So now after that once that
threshold limit is reached we will stop
the future call to product. So now all
the future calls there is no
hit to the product we will fail the call
immediately.
We will not block the thread. We will
fail the call immediately.
Okay. And we will wait for some time.
After that we will check if product
service is healthy or not. So it will do
a trial testing after some time. Hey, it
will send some sample or you can say
that the test calls. Hey, is product
services responding properly or not? If
yes then only it will allow future calls
to the product. Okay. So whatever we
have covered here it is
can be understand it can be understand
through this state diagram.
So start from here. This is the initial
state. Okay. So for any application
the best case is closed. Closed means
that all calls are allowed to downstream
service means everything is going good.
Okay. Circuit is closed. Circuit is
closed means just remember always
sometime many time engineer got confused
that hey circuit is closed means no
calls. No. So see consider this as a
circuit. So when the circuit is closed
then only electricity will flow. When
the circuit is open then electricity
current will break. Understand it is
just to remember this. So when the
circuit is closed
all calls are allowed to downstream
service.
Now if failure limit cross the threshold
let's say five failure, six failure
whatever the threshold we will set. If
that many failures so see there could be
some success, there could be some
failure while making a call to
downstream. But if the failure limit
threshold value is crossed then it moved
from closed state to open state. Now
open state means
no calls allowed to downstream service
and fail the call immediately.
So after this it wait for certain time
which is like you can say the timeout
period. After that let's say it could be
10 second 5 second 15 second that hey
for 5 second or 10 second no call is
allowed. After that it move to half open
state. Half open state says that allow
only limited number of test calls to
downstream and track their success rate.
Say I say that hey allowed only three
calls allowed only five calls. So very
limited number of calls we will send it
to the downstream and then track their
success rate. If the success rate is
100% then circuit can be closed again.
But if the success rate is not 100%
the state goes back to open.
Okay. So whatever we have seen this can
be easily represented through this state
of circuit breaker.
Okay. And let's see its implementation.
It's very easy. So we have already seen
that we don't need uh individual
dependency of circuit breaker. It's all
come with the resilience 4j itself. So
we already have that dependency added as
part of previous u retry and all. So
this pom.xml
we need to add this resilience 4j
dependency. This is the same no change
it's just a controller class to expose
an API through which we can invoke this
order service
uh method
and this is a f client like no change
it's like uh we are using ureka server
so that's why I haven't provided any URL
right so that's already we have seen in
the previous one. So there is no change
here. Now in the order service we have a
method right it is invoking the order
service method invoke product API. So
this is actually where I am invoking the
downstream product. So now at top of it
I have put this circuit breaker. So I
have given it a name. This is the name
product service and this is the fallback
method. So this is the fallback method.
Remember that this fallback method
always get invoked for each failure
attempt.
Okay. So whenever you are not able to
invoke this product service, this
fallback method get invoked.
Okay. So this is one thing we have to
add a circuit breaker annotation
and this is the configuration we have to
add in application.properties.
So this is very important. So understand
this configuration uh properly that why
we need this many.
So the first thing is
resilience 4j.tcircuit breaker.instance.
This is the name we have given product
service. Now see the first one is
sliding window type and the second one
is sliding window size. So both are
associated.
So here if you see that when you are
choosing the count based as the window
type and the size what does it means is
it will track the n number of recent
call. So here it will track the 10
recent calls and based on that it will
find out whether there is any failure or
not. So this is helpful when you are
currently in a closed state.
So when you are in a closed state and
means all calls are allowed and you have
to identify whether a threshold has been
crossed or not. Okay. So there should be
some window on which some request comes
which could be success which could be
failure which could be success which
could be failure. Right? So this window
size is this. Okay. So window size is
this and I am using countbas. So count
based means
10 calls.
So use the last 10 calls.
Okay. There another is time based. So
it's not call then 10 second.
In 10 second
how whatever the call it could be 10 20
100 doesn't matter. Now it's a time
base. So it's a time base. What is the
size? 10 second.
So in 10 seconds whatever the call is
there
right some call could be success some
call could be failure now based on that
we will find out whether the threshold
has been crossed or not. So first we
have to determine the window. So this is
helping us to determine our window. Okay
never get confused it with like uh rate
limiter sliding windows and all right it
is totally different. This is count
based means when we are giving a 10 so
means 10 calls
last 10 calls we have to consider and
based on that we will find out a
threshold value okay so first two is
clear then is minimum number of calls
so minimum number of calls so see why we
required is let's say uh we have only
two calls let's say count based and And
the window size you have given two say
suppose or even if you are using time
based 10 second in the 10 second you
only got two calls
and your threshold is let's say hey 50%
of the traffic is fail
then consider it as a failure
but here when there is only two calls
and what does 50% means only one even if
there is one failure now you will
consider that hey product service is
down is it is it not a false positive
Right? It's a false alarm. Only one
request fails, it could be because of
like uh if you retry it might pass.
Okay? So when the number is very low
then there is a chance that there is a
false positive.
Okay. So that's why minimum number of
calls says that hey
when this number of calls
reach then only start evaluating the
failure rate. Okay so minimum at least
this many calls should be present then
only after that start evaluating the
failure.
Okay.
Then another is failure rate threshold.
This is percentage. So
circuit moves to open state once the
threshold limit reach. So if 50% of the
traffic
is a failure in a window in this window
in this window if 50% of the traffic
failed then it move from closed to open
state.
Then another is wait duration in open
state. So once the circuit moves to open
state how much time it has to wait. Okay
before it move to half open. So 10
second it has to stay in the open state
before it move to
half open state.
Now once the circuit move to the half
open state then it has to try some
calls. Okay. How many? So I have told
three calls. So permitted number of
calls in half open state is three. So
means it will call three times. It will
allow three calls to go to the
downstream and then it will evaluate the
success rate.
Okay. So these are all the
configurations uh which is important
and we will see with an uh output also
that would be a little bit more clear
and also this is also important that by
default circuit breaker record all
runtime exception and error as a
failure. If you don't specify anything
all runtime exception and error it will
track. But if you want this control in
your hand you can use this two
configuration.
One is record exception. Another is
ignore exception. So it's a
commaepparated value you can give that
what all the exception you only have to
track. Okay. And what all exceptions you
have to ignore. So this way you can have
more control over it. Otherwise if you
don't give it it will take care of all
the runtime exceptions and error.
Okay. So this is the very minimal code
you required for the circuit breaker to
work. Okay, only configurations and this
circuit breaker annotation.
Now with this configuration just check
this output. Okay, so we can also run it
in the intelligent but here we'll show
you once then I will run in the
intelligent. So first time I hit so this
is the first call I made. What I did is
order service is calling the product
service and the product server I haven't
started it. So no matter how many times
order will try to invoke product it will
always fail. So that's the uh use case I
am going to test now with the above
configurations.
So let me zoom it a bit. So I made a
first hit. I try to invoke this endpoint
this endpoint. So this endpoint it will
uh invoke this method invoke product
API. Invoke product API will call get
product by ID but the product server
itself I haven't started it. So
definitely it will fail. Okay.
So
it tried first time see it reached till
it tried to hit it tried to find an
instance of a product service but since
it is not a load balancer not able to
find the instance.
So first call I made it got failed and
it print this fallback method
system.out.print which I am printing.
Now what is how many is the failure
count? One. What is the minimum count we
have sent? Minimum call should be five.
Till that don't even start counting the
failure.
The window size we have is 10. Threshold
is 50. So 50 of a window size means five
failure is a threshold. Once the five
failure has been reached in a window, it
will move to the open state. But till
now failure is only one. Then I make a
second call.
Second call is also failed. Failure
count is now two but minimum is five.
Window is 10. Threshold is five.
Third call is also failed. Again no
issues. It is still in closed state. It
is actually hitting try to hit the
downstream but failure count is three.
Minimum call is five. Window size is 10.
Threshold is 50% of window size that is
five. Fourth call is again it tried to
go to the downstream.
Fifth call. So now what if if you see
that fifth call is also failed. So here
if you see not able to invoke the
product service. So it also tried to hit
the downstream. fifth. Now the failure
count is five. Now here if you see the
minimum call
now it is matched.
So now the minimum call is matched. Now
it will see hey in this window mine is
count based right 10. So its threshold
was 50%. So five failure if there is a
five failure then it would be considered
as like a threshold cross. So my
failure count is five and the threshold
is five and the window size is 10. Okay.
So in the last within last 10 calls. So
till till now the first five call itself
got failed. So it's within a window and
threshold is crossed. So see now it move
from
closed to open state. It change circuit
breaker change the state and here after
10 second we have configured that right
what is the wait time in the open 10
second we have configured that so here
if you see after 10 second from 20 now
after 10 second 30 it automatically
change from open to half open so how
automatically
after a specific time it automatically
change from open to half open I will
tell you uh later in this uh video
itself
Okay. So here if you see like after
exactly 10 seconds whatever we have
configured the status changed from open
to half open. Now after that I again so
in half open how many permitted calls we
have given three. So now I made a first
trial call. Okay. So this is the maximum
trial call we have set is three. So
first trial call is also failed
but it tried to invoke the load
balancer. So means it is tried to invoke
the downstream. The second call also it
tried to invoke the downstream but that
is also failed. The third trial also it
got failed where it tried to invoke the
downstream but now our limit is reach
the third. So
from half open it will go back to open
again because all three failed success
rate is zero. Okay. So only in case of
100% success rate it move back to close.
Okay. So it goes from half open to open
because success rate is not 100%.
So here if you see the we all know that
resilience 4j uses a we till now we have
seen. So AOP intercept this add the red
circuit breaker uh annotation and it
pass to this class circuit breaker state
machine on Java. This is a framework
which is available in resilience 4j. So
open this class check it out. So this is
just one sample method in this class.
Okay. So here if you see that depending
upon which state you are at. So let's
say currently I am at closed state.
Okay. At closed state you are making one
call to downstream and if any error
comes so it this method get invoked. So
for every error every exception it check
does it exceed the threshold.
Okay if it exceed the threshold yes and
it is closed state
move to open now. So if yes threshold
exceeded and it is in closed then move
to open. So for every failure it checks
this kind of method right and based on
particular state it move to another
state. So open this class put a debugger
point you can check it out and you will
get to know that how it move from one
state to another.
But one question might be coming to you
right. Okay, for every failure call we
are checking if a state need to be
changed or not. That makes sense, right?
I make a call got failed. I am tracking
what is the threshold value. I do
computation and if the threshold
crossed, I change the state from close
to open.
Right? And even from half open if I am
at half open if the trial all trial I
make a call and based on that I will
evaluate if it all 100% I will go back
to closed or half open or open but one
open question is when my state isn't
currently open
then how after a specific weight let's
say 10 second It automatically moves to
half open state. How
how does it change from open to half
open?
Okay. So the answer is it uses scheduled
threadpool executor.
So if you see the circuit breaker state
machine on Java itself the same class
there you will find an open state
method. So method for open state. So in
that you will see
okay. So schedule threadpull executor
it schedule a task means it will submit
a task to a scheduleuler to this
executor and this is the task it submit.
What is the task it is submitting to
half open state means transition from
open to
half open
after what time? This is the delay wait
duration let's say 10
it time unit is in millisecond let's say
after 10 millisecond
change from open to half open. So this
is the task which need to be run after
this much time.
So scheduled threadpull exeutor with the
usage of this scheduled threadpool
executor we can
change or we can perform certain task
after a particular delay and I have
already explained the schedule thread
pool executor in the Java playlist. You
can check it out how to use it.
But in interview
uh one level more deep information is
useful because interviewer can ask okay
with the usage of schedule threadpull
executor
I can perform this task but how this
internally works.
How does schedule threadpull executor
works? So schedule thread pool executor
actually make use of delayed Q.
So consider this as a Q where
whenever we put schedule right. So here
I am putting dot schedule uh schedule
executor service dot schedule. So this
task
is now handed over to this Q delayed Q
which is known as delayed Q. So the task
with the minimum delay is always at the
head. Minimum delay means the task which
will get expired first like uh this task
will run after 1 second. This task will
run task two will get run after uh 10
seconds. So you can uh say that the task
which is going to run very next is
always at the head. Okay. So which data
structure we can use to implement this
delete Q is priority Q. We can make use
of priority Q and sort based on this
minimum delay time. Whichever task has
the very minimum delay time, it should
be at the head because this delay is
going to expire early so that this task
would be ready to get executed first.
Okay. So one thing is delayed queue.
Another thing is we have a worker
thread. We have a worker thread. So
whenever the schedule thread pool
executor we are creating an object of
this one, we also tell how many worker
thread we want it which will work on
this executor.
Okay. So now what happen is let's say
assume that
in this delayed queue
this is our task one which has let's say
10 second is still time remaining before
it delay get expired and the task one is
ready to get executed. Now let's say
thread
one look at the head. Hey can I pick
this task? Are you ready? Okay, so each
available worker thread will look at the
head of the delayed queue.
If the task delay is not yet expired, so
there is still 10 second left. Okay, it
should not be executed now. Then what
this thread will do? This thread will go
in a block state. Okay, then thread will
wait go into block state for how much
time? For the same amount of time. So it
will check okay this task will ready
after 10 second. So let me also block
for 10 second. It will go in a wait
state for 10 second.
After the 10 second the OS wake up the
thread. OS wake up the thread after this
10 second after this. So this whatever
the delay is remaining right for the
same remaining delay time this thread
will go into the uh wait state block
state and OS will wake it up after that
much time and after that much time this
thread will also be ready. uh this task
is also ready to get executed. Okay. So
this thread now will go and pick the
task from the head and start executing
it.
Now other thread will start looking at
the next task in the delayed queue.
There could be multiple tasks. Task two,
task three, task four. So now other
threads will start looking at the next
uh task which is present into the delay
cube. If that task is not yet ready then
thread will again get blocked.
Okay. So it is possible that multiple
threads which are available is looking
at the head and all let's say thread one
thread 2 thread three all are looking at
this head task one which has 10 second
to still delay time is present.
So multiple thread look that hey can I
pick the task because all threads are
available. they have to look at the
queue to see if any task is present so
that they can pick it up. So now this
task has still 10 seconds uh delay time
present. So what this thread will do
this thread can't do anything. Okay. So
they all goes to wait
and I told you that how much time the
same amount of time the remaining delay
time they will all goes to
wait or block state then OS will invoke
it and out of that only one will go and
pick this task. So you can say that that
is your uh lock one of the task one of
the thread will use the lock and pick
this task and then remaining thread will
now start looking at the next item
present into the delay Q. If that task
is still not ready then again those
thread will wait for the remaining delay
time
and it will be in the wait state till
the task is ready.
I hope if interviewer ask you about how
there is a very similar question also
you can say that uh the WhatsApp message
the WhatsApp message get automatically
deleted
after
24 hours let's say how how you will
implement it so nothing but this delayed
Q only okay so there are many uh big
companies like you can say that delayed
cues
frameworks are available right and we
can easily implement this feature using
delete cube. So this is very popular
interview questions like how you will
implement the disappearing message
feature through delete cube easy.
Okay guys, so if you have any doubt let
me know in the comment section we can
discuss further. Okay, bye.